<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Earl of Danby's answer to Sr. Robert Howards book, entituled An account of the state of His Majesties revenue as it was left by the Earl of Danby at Lady-day, 1679.</title>
            <author>Leeds, Thomas Osborne, Duke of, 1631-1712.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1680</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 51 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A49985</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L921</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R2753</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12577702</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12577702</idno>
            <idno type="VID">63646</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A49985)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 63646)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 672:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Earl of Danby's answer to Sr. Robert Howards book, entituled An account of the state of His Majesties revenue as it was left by the Earl of Danby at Lady-day, 1679.</title>
                  <author>Leeds, Thomas Osborne, Duke of, 1631-1712.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 14 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Randall Tayler,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1680.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Howard, Robert, --  Sir, 1626-1698. --  Account of the state of His Majesties revenue.</term>
               <term>Finance --  England --  History.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:63646:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE EARL OF DANBYS ANSWER TO Sr. Robert Howard's BOOK, ENTITULED An Account of the State of his Majeſties Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venue; as it was Left by the Earl of <hi>Danby</hi> at <hi>Lady-Day,</hi> 1679.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Randall Tayler,</hi> 1680.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:63646:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:63646:2"/>
            <head>THE EARL OF DANBYS ANSWER TO Sr. Robert Howard's ACCOUNT, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>I Know not whether I ſhould find fault, or thank Sr. <hi>Robert How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard</hi> for his late Book, called <hi>An Account of the State of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties Revenue, as it was left at Lady-Day</hi> 1679, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Becauſe, upon Examination it will appear to have done me no injury, and has ſhewed the Examiner that there was nothing to be ſaid in Juſtification of any other part of his Book, but only what concerned the State of the Revenue, as it was found by Me at <hi>June</hi> 1673. and left at <hi>Lady-Day,</hi> 1679.</p>
            <p>Sir <hi>Robert</hi> does likewiſe ſhew how he deteſts ſuch Scurrilous Language as the Examiner is full of; for in my Anſwer, I have but once called a certain untruth, a notorious Falſhood, and Sr. <hi>Robert</hi> ſeems to be much offended at the Expreſſion.</p>
            <p>He ſhews himſelf alſo far more ingenuous than the Examiner was, for he confeſſes many Errors in the Examiners Book, although the Exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miner be very poſitive in the defence of them; viz. <hi>In his abſolute affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:63646:3"/>that my Sallary was never included in ſecret ſervice. In his double charging of</hi> 200000 l. <hi>on the one fifth of the Exciſe. And in ſaying that the whole Tax upon the firſt Act for Disbanding the Army was come into the Exchequer in my time, &amp;c.</hi> which Sir <hi>Robert</hi> is ſo much my friend as to acknowledge, he believes to be otherwiſe, although he confeſſes, Fol. 7. <hi>that he has not given himſelf the trouble to examine it;</hi> and in the ſame page he ſayes, <hi>he ſhall not meddle with their Arguments</hi> (meaning I ſuppoſe the Examiners Arguments and mine;) ſo as I perceive we muſt ſtand upon our own legs for what either of us have ſaid, he being reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved <hi>only to give the Publick an Account how the Revenue was left at Lady day,</hi> 1679. <hi>and not to meddle with Politick Diſputes, nor matters of State,</hi> which fills the greater number of Folioes in the Examiners Book.</p>
            <p>Sir <hi>Robert</hi> does alſo know that if all the matters of Fact contained in his Book were true, it could be no Crime in me, that the Revenue was more or leſs in Debt at my leaving it: unleſs I had either leſſened the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of the Revenue, or not truly anſwered the whole Income accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his Majeſties Directions: or had diverted any of the Moneys gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven by Parliament to other uſes than were limited by the ſeveral Acts; and he does not pretend to ſay any thing either as to the leſſening, or not anſwering the whole Revenue; (but on the contrary confeſſes the Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue to be increaſed in my time.) And for diverting any part thereof, he ſpeaks as if ſome others did complain to him of it; but I do not under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand that he directly charges any ſuch thing himſelf; nor can any man do it but with great untruth: inſomuch that were it not for ſome expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons not ſo becoming a mans own Secretary to be guilty of, and that the time of publiſhing his Book hath not been ſo generouſly taken, as ſome men of Honour would have done, I ſhould not only have forgiven but have thanked Sir <hi>Robert</hi> for the opportunity of clearing the integrity of my ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagement in the Treaſury, however I may have been wanting in thoſe abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities which God hath given to himſelf above other men: And he ought not to blame me, but my underſtanding, if I could not always comprehend ſuch Schemes and Projects of his concerning the Revenue, whereof I have ſome ſtill in my cuſtody, which I muſt acknowledge I do not yet underſtand, any more than I did when I firſt received them.</p>
            <p>That which makes me complain of the time Sir <hi>Robert</hi> has taken to divulge his Book, is, becauſe it may be too reaſonably ſuſpected, that thoſe Reaſons he gives for having deferred it ſo many moneths, are not ſo pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable, as ſome other reaſons may be, which he does not think fit to give, becauſe <hi>if his Relations were not well at Tunbridge;</hi> yet it ſeems <hi>he was well himſelf;</hi> and how a man whoſe Office and Dwelling is in the Exche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer, and who hath ſo great a controul over it, <hi>could want either Records or Certificates from other Offices</hi> ſo long as he hath taken to ſatisfie his Friends inquiry is not very likely.</p>
            <p>But theſe Reaſons were likely; <hi>Firſt,</hi> That ſuch a Book as this (though I dare ſay underſtood by very few that reads it,) would make a great noiſe againſt a man in my condition, in the time of a Parliaments Sitting. <hi>Secondly,</hi> That in Probability, it would be impoſſible for me under a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finement, (and who am without Power to ſend for any Records or Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, and who am now without the help of thoſe Officers who acted then under me) to give any full anſwer (during the ſitting of Parliament)
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:63646:3"/>to what he has found ſo many months little enough to do, who had all the Leaſure and Helps for it he could deſire.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That being under Accuſations in Parliament, I might probably be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led upon to anſwer them at this time; So as I ſhould not only want lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, but in all Likely-hood I could not have my thoughts free to attend to ſuch a matter as this, when I had ſo much greater concerns upon my Hands.</p>
            <p>And laſtly, Though it contain nothing of Criminal in it; Yet it might be hoped that any ſmall weight, which could not receive an Anſwer in due time, might contribute to the heightning of mens ill Opinions, againſt one he thought not yet enough Loaded with falſe Aſperſions.</p>
            <p>If this was the Deſign, (as I have too much reaſon to believe, both from what I have ſaid, and becauſe otherwiſe I do not believe he would have troubled himſelf, to have Writ, what he knows will be found to have ſo many miſtakes) I do acknowledge, that he hath gained ſo much of his deſign, that I ſhall not be able, under my Circumſtances, to give ſo full an Anſwer at preſent, as I hope to do hereafter; If my Condition will per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit: And I doubt not but to make it appear, that I have ſaid nothing in my firſt anſwer, but what I have ſtill good reaſon to believe True.</p>
            <p>In the mean time I ſhall endeavour to ſhew the Fallacies which are in many parts of his Book. The wrong State of the Queſtions to ſuch Officers from whence he hath got Certificates; ſo as though the Certi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficates may be true, yet they are not properly applied by Sr. <hi>Robert.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And laſtly, The diſ-ingenuous ſwelling of the Account, to make a noiſe to the world of a great Debt (beſides the Anticipations) which will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear to be no more any Ground for accuſing my Management, than it hath been of my Predeceſſors, and muſt be of thoſe who ſucceed me in the Treaſury. As the Examiner I doubt not but knew very well, when he made no mention of it in the Range of his Malice, who made appear ſufficiently, that he would not have ſpared thoſe, nor any other particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars to have loaded his Charge; but that he knew how eaſily they would be anſwered.</p>
            <p>As to the fallacious Gloſſes (of which he makes great uſe through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out his Book) he begins Folio 2. <hi>That the third Quarter of the Eighteen months Tax was ſigned (Osborn)</hi> And hopes from thence to have it infer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re'd, that I had the diſpoſal of ſome of the Money of that Quarter, which I can prove that himſelf knows the contrary (as well as that I never was Lord <hi>Treaſurer</hi> under the Title of Sr. <hi>Thomas Osborn;</hi>) And from the ſame Reaſon of my having ſigned that Quarter (which was done at the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt of my Lord <hi>Clifford,</hi> and for ſatisfaction of the Creditors on that Quarter; that they ſhould not be Poſt-poned by my coming to the Treaſury,) he would alſo have it believed, that the 21163 l. 6 s. 8 d. ſaid in my Book to be charged by my Lord <hi>Clifford</hi> on the fourth Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of that Tax, was not ſo; But I muſt acknowledg he inſiſts not much upon that matter; but ends that Paragraph, Folio 3, with a Confeſſion, <hi>that be knows nothing of it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>His next pretence is, that upon the three laſt Quarters of that Tax, there appears to have been paid into the Exchequer, <hi>the Sum of</hi> 584718 l. 7 s. 5 d. which I call but 565498 l. 13 s. 10 d. ½, all the Charges be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing deducted (as the forgiving any Receivers, or their Securities, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>)
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:63646:4"/>which is notwithſtanding made received in the Exchequer; as if it came to be diſpoſable Money to the Kings uſe. And although I cannot now have the ſight of Originals, I have great Confidence, that the Certificates I received of that matter before my leaving the Staff will prove my Computations to be true, when all the Circumſtances are Examined.</p>
            <p>In Folio's, Third, Fourth, Fifth, and part of the Sixth, he takes great Pains to ſhow, <hi>that I did hinder and divert the Money on the one Fifth of the Exciſe, from being Paid into the Exchequer, as the Act of Parliment did direct; and ſays,</hi> Mr. <hi>Duncomb the Gold-ſmith did often complain to him of it.</hi> The truth is, I have ſo often heard Mr. <hi>Duncomb</hi> complain of Sr. <hi>Robert</hi> himſelf, that he ſhould not for his own ſake much regard his Complaints; But in this matter it happned, that the 200000, l. being Lent by Mr. <hi>Kent</hi> and <hi>Duncomb,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Kent</hi> then being Receiver of the Cuſtoms, from whom Sir. <hi>Iohn Iames,</hi> Major <hi>Huntingdon, &amp;c.</hi> (who were then Pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſters of the Army) were to receive 2000, l. a Week out of the Cuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toms: And the ſaid Sr. <hi>Iohn Iames,</hi> Major <hi>Huntingdon, &amp;c.</hi> being Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceivers of the Exciſe, ſo as the one Fifth was to be Paid by them, to the ſaid Mr. <hi>Kent</hi> and <hi>Duncomb:</hi> An agreement was made, or Pretended to be made amongſt themſelves, (and without any Direction of mine,) for the Accommodation of the Kings ſervice, by Mr. <hi>Kent</hi> and Mr. <hi>Dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>combs</hi> taking the 2000, l. a Week, (which was in their own Hands) for part of the Money due to them from Sr. <hi>Iohn Iames, &amp;c.</hi> upon the one Fifth of the Exciſe: And although ſome differences did at laſt ariſe in this matter betwixt them; yet it was ſetled in the Kings preſence at the Treaſury Chamber before my leaving the Staff, and was ſo far from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing diverted by me, either from being Paid into the Exchequer, as the Act directed, or from being paid to any other uſes than the Direction of the ſaid Act did appoint; that I will put the truth or Falſhood of what either he or I, have writ about the Revenue, upon the proof of that Parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular. <hi>And for the</hi> 83400, <hi>l. which he ſays was unpaid of the</hi> 200000, l. I confeſs I underſtand not how that could be, when Mr. <hi>Kent,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Duncomb</hi> might force the Receivers of the Exciſe to pay what was due to them, on the one Fifth when ever they Pleaſed; Beſides, that I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve at the time of my leaving the Staff, there was 52000, l. in Mr. <hi>Kents</hi> hands, by an arrear of the 2000 l. a Week on the Cuſtoms, then due to Sr. <hi>Iohn Iames, &amp;c.</hi> By which Mr. <hi>Kent</hi> and <hi>Duncomb,</hi> might pay themſelves ſo much of whatſoever Sum was remaining unpaid to them at that time, on the one Fifth of the Exciſe. And in truth the whole matter concerned me no more, than it did Sr. <hi>Robert</hi> himſelf; and I have ſome reaſon to think, that the Examiner was not ſo ill inſtructed, as to have left that Sum out of his Charge (eſpecially having mentioned it in his ſixth Folio,) if it could have been made any Argument againſt me, which (as I have already ſaid) it cannot be; Unleſs I had either given Orders to the Receivers of the Exciſe not to pay the Fifth according to the Act, or had given them Orders for applying any part of it, to other Uſes, than the Act directed; either of which, I do Challenge Sr. <hi>Robert,</hi> or any body elſe, to prove, and therefore it was, that I called it, <hi>Noto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly falſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The next head wherein he is knowingly unwilling to do me Right, is, <hi>about the Poll Bill,</hi> which I find I have ſpoke ſo fully to, in my anſwer to
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:63646:4"/>the Examiner, that I ſee he thinks not fit to make any reply to what I have there ſaid; But only deſigns to make it a piece of my ill manage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that 186585. <hi>l.</hi> 18. <hi>s.</hi> 9. <hi>d.</hi> (for which he ſays the Commiſſioners of the Treaſury have given Aſſignments) is added as a Charge upon the Revenue, to make up his Additional Charge at the end of his Book, to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mount to the ſum of 655634. <hi>l.</hi> 19. <hi>s.</hi> 6. <hi>d,</hi> whereas no body knows bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than Sr. <hi>Robert,</hi> that the Poll Bill was eſtimated to 400000. l. at leaſt; That Credit was given by the Act for 300000. <hi>l.</hi> in Money upon it, and an indefinite Credit for ſtores beyond the 300000. <hi>l.;</hi> So as no part of the Money or Credits lent upon that Act, was believed would ever have affected the Revenue at all; <hi>And if ready Money was promiſed to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny body upon that Act,</hi> which was not Performed, I am ſure no man can ſay they had that Promiſe from me; And moreover though Sr. <hi>Robert</hi> puts this, 186585, <hi>l.</hi> 18. <hi>s.</hi> 9. <hi>d. as a Debt due only to the Eaſt-land Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants,</hi> I remember that the ſum demanded by them in my time was far leſs, (and as I think not full 40000. l.) ſo that I believe, that reckoning muſt be ſwelled by other Demands, and is no fault of mine if there be now ſuch a Charge on the Revenue.</p>
            <p>In Folio the 8th. I find Sr. <hi>Robert</hi> brings <hi>the ſame Paper, which was quoted by the Examiner for a State of the Revenue, as it was made up by my</hi> Lord <hi>Clifford</hi> 10th <hi>of</hi> June 1673. I confeſs I do not ſee any uſe he makes of it; But he hopes perhaps that others will, when he has told them, <hi>that the Original of that Paper was drawn by Sr.</hi> Philip LLoyd; But that can by no means a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree with Sr. <hi>Philips</hi> own letter, which is Printed in my Anſwer; and Sr. <hi>Robert</hi> muſt give me alſo leave to doubt it; becauſe I never ſaw nor heard of any ſuch Paper from my Lord <hi>Clifford,</hi> who would Probably rather have deſigned ſuch a paper for my Information, than any bodies elſe, unleſs the King himſelf. But the Examiner having ſaid, <hi>That he has a Copy of it under Sr.</hi> Philips <hi>own hand,</hi> may put this matter out of Diſpute, if Sr. <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert</hi> have but intereſt enough to procure that Copy from the Exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miner.</p>
            <p>Thoſe points I have already ſpoke to, (as having been very Diſ-inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuouſly handled by Sr. <hi>Robert</hi>) I take to be all the matters of Fact menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned by him, till he comes to the main buſineſs of his Book (beginning Folio 11th. about the State of the Revenue at <hi>Lady-Day,</hi> 1679.) Except<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a miſtake of the Printer, of Forty Pounds, Folio the 2d, which he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieves, Folio 7th. hath been made in the Examiners Computation, <hi>to the Sum of above three Millions (although Sr.</hi> Robert <hi>calls it a Repetition of the former Sum,</hi> (which it is not) And excepting an acknowledgment he makes Folio 3d. <hi>that the Cuſtoms never yielded ſo much as in my time:</hi> And excepting the Head about ſecret Service, Folio 7th, where he Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſes that the Sum of 252467. l. 10. s. 5. <hi>d. is all that was Paid for ſecret Service in Mr.</hi> Berties <hi>name, in three compleat Years ending</hi> Lady-Day, 1679; But does add, 14640. <hi>l. in the ſaid three Years,</hi> which he does un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hanſomely (and contrary to his own knowledge) Inſinuate, as if the year<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Sums for New-years Gifts (which I am not provided to ſay whether they be that Sum he names for three Years or not) <hi>were privately di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected to be diſtributed by Mr.</hi> Bertie; Which on the contrary he knows was the Kings conſtant yearly Allowances to ſeveral of his Servants, and Officers, long before my time, and without any alteration of them that
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:63646:5"/>I know in my time, ſo that I might juſtly have added this amongſt the reſt which have had ſuch diſingenuous applications made of them; but that I am not furniſhed to anſwer, nor do I know what he means, by that Sum which (with the 252467 l. to Mr. <hi>Bertie,</hi> and the 14640 l. for New-Years Gifts) he pretends to be for ſecret Service, and to make the Sum of 309556 <hi>l. in the ſaid three Years;</hi> nor do I know to whom any ſuch Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney hath been paid for ſecret ſervice in that time more than the ſaid 252467 l. 10 s. 5 d. to Mr. <hi>Bertie,</hi> and of which (as I have ſaid in my for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Anſwer) 57763 l. at leaſt has been disburſt for publick uſes, and Sir <hi>Robert</hi> may perhaps be miſtaken in this matter as well as he confeſſes (in the very next Paragraph) that the Examiner was, in his poſitive Averrment, Fol. 11. of that Book, <hi>that my Sallery was never included</hi> in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret Service.</p>
            <p>Sir <hi>Robert</hi> begins Fol. 11. of his Book, with the Examiners Charge, and my Deductions; but confeſſes in Fol. 13. <hi>A miſtake of the Examiner, in that Charge, to the Sum of</hi> 58352 l. 9 s. 6 d. which it ſeems is charged by the Examiner as part of the Total Charge, beſides all the Advance-Moneys; of which the 58352 l. is part, and which I could not have known but by Sir <hi>Robert</hi>'s help; ſo as by that computation, the Examiners Charge upon the three great Branches of the Revenue at <hi>Lady Day</hi> 1679. ought to have been but 1427218 l. 6 s. 10 d. and whether it may not be yte leſs by ſuch double Charges, which I cannot know for want of the particulars of the General Charge, is very uncertain.</p>
            <p>The particulars which I ſay ought to be deducted from that Charge, are the nine following, <hi>viz.</hi>
               <list>
                  <item>1. For the Advance on the Exciſe.—270000 l.</item>
                  <item>2. For the Advance on the Hearth-Duty.—150000.</item>
                  <item>3. To be Diſcharged by Orders to the Commiſſioners of Exciſe on the firſt Act of Disbanding.—101000.</item>
                  <item>4. More by Tallyes on the Surplus of the Exciſe for 30000 l. and 99000 l. being no Charge on the Rent, except the Surplus fail.—129000.</item>
                  <item>5. More by Tallyes which were to pay the Forces from <hi>Lady-Day</hi> 79 forwards to <hi>July</hi> following, which was 97 Days be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond my Time.—59588.</item>
                  <item>6. More by Tallyes on the Cuſtoms made uſe of to carry on the Service of the Navy and Ordnance beyond that ſaid <hi>Lady-Day</hi> 79. 35000.</item>
                  <item>7. More by Tallyes, ſtruck for Penſions upon the two laſt Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of the Exciſe, <hi>viz. Chriſtmaſs</hi> 78. and <hi>Lady-Day</hi> 79. for payment of which Money, was left in the hand of the Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oners of Exciſe about.—33000.</item>
                  <item>8. More by Tallyes on the Cuſtoms reſtored for Tynn depoſited in Mr. <hi>Kents</hi> hands.—15000.</item>
                  <item>9. More by Tallyes on the Cuſtoms Accounted by the Examiner to be unpaid to Mr. <hi>Mountague,</hi> which were paid in my Time. 2342.</item>
                  <item>Totall Sum 794930 l.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:63646:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>I agree with Sr. <hi>Robert,</hi> Fol. 12. <hi>That the Examination of theſe Parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars muſt determine the true State of the Charge left then on the Kings Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venue;</hi> and by this Declaration of his own, that it muſt do ſo; it appears that Sr. <hi>Robert</hi> did not think any great weight was to be laid upon his following particulars of 655634 l. 19 s. 6 d. by which he would ſwell the Debt to 2074879 l. 16 s. 0 d.</p>
            <p>But I can by no means agree with him, nor admit his reaſons, why none of the aboveſaid deductions ſhould be allowed, <hi>but</hi> 59588 <hi>l. to the Forces, and</hi> 2342 <hi>l. to Mr.</hi> Mountague, (nor does he agree with himſelf in ſome of them) and for the 4395 l. 3 s. 6 <hi>d. which he alloweth on the Tynn <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> it will appear in its proper place to be over and above the 15000 l. deducted for the Tynn in my Computation; and muſt therefore in its due place be added to my former Deductions.</p>
            <p>As to the <hi>Advances</hi> which are his firſt Exception, it is to be obſerved, that Sir <hi>Robert,</hi> as well as the Examiner, makes uſe of <hi>a pretended Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per of the Lord Cliffords;</hi> but omits to draw from thence (as the Exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner doth) a State how the Revenue was left Charged by my Lord <hi>Clif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford;</hi> and yet without doing that, it is impoſſible to compare whether the Debt be increaſed or decreaſed ſince that time: Inſomuch that this omiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion muſt be for ſome other end, and ſerves particularly that it may not be ſeen (as it muſt be by drawing ſuch a State) and as it was in the Examiners Book, that <hi>the Advances in my Lord Cliffords time were Accounted no part of the Debt upon the Revenue,</hi> and I wiſh that all his Majeſties Debts were in ſuch a condition as would always diſcharge it ſelf, and yet leave his Majeſty the full uſe of his Revenue: and although Sr. <hi>Robert</hi> be of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther opinion, I cannot help believing, that if all his Majeſties Revenue was brought into the ſame way, which I brought the Exciſe (<hi>viz.</hi> of being Let upon a certain great Rent, and that ſecured by a great Sum advanced, and the Overplus (after certain Salleries paid for management) to be to the Kings own uſe, with an incouragement to the Managers of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſing their Wages by a ſmall allowance out of every pound which they can improve beyond the Sum ſecured, the whole Revenue would be encreaſed by the Induſtry of the Managers (who in that caſe work for themſelves as well as for the King) much more than would pay the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt of the Sums advanced; as hath been made appear by the Overplus of the Exciſe in my Time; and which I fear it would not have done by any who had only taken pains for the King, without any proſpect of gain to themſelves more than their bare Salleries; But to conclude this Point, ſince it hath never heretofore been reckoned in the State of the Debt (not by the Examiner himſelf) and his Majeſty having the Uſe of his whole Revenue notwithſtanding the Advance Money, and that Sir <hi>Roberts</hi> beſt Reaſon, is only, <hi>that he is of Opinion it might be better done by management without Advance:</hi> I ſuppoſe theſe firſt and ſecond Deducti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons will be thought but reaſonable, and I muſt here deſire it may be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, that Sir <hi>Robert,</hi> Fol. 12. ſayes, <hi>I have reckoned the Advance on the the Exciſe</hi> 20000 <hi>l. more than really it was;</hi> and yet in the end of the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſame Paragraph, <hi>he confeſſes that the Advance on the Exciſe indeed was as much as I call it,</hi> viz. 270000 l.</p>
            <p>My third Deduction is 101000 l. to be diſcharged by Orders to the Commiſſioners of Exciſe, &amp;c. as aforeſaid.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:63646:6"/>
            <p>To which Sir <hi>Robert</hi> gives no colour of contradiction, only he ſays, <hi>it was part of a double Security given to</hi> Sir <hi>John James, &amp;c.</hi> by which he acknowledges there was ſo much Money in their hands for the diſcharging of Tallyes; and then, <hi>whether it was in the Examiners Charge or no</hi> is no great matter, nor is it leſs to be allowed for one of the Deductions; only here I do obſerve Sir <hi>Robert</hi> is ſo intimate with the Examiner, that he knows of what particulars the Examiners Charge is made up, which I ſhould have been glad to have known either from the Examiner or Sir <hi>Robert,</hi> and then I could have anſwered more particularly every part of the Charge, in the ſame method as I do now ſet down every particular of the Deductions which ought to be allowed.</p>
            <p>My fourth Deduction is 129000 <hi>l:</hi> by Tallyes on the Surplus of the Exciſe, which I ſay is no Charge upon the Rent, Fol. 10. of my Book; and yet Sir <hi>Robert,</hi> Fol. 15. of his ſayes, that I ſay it is no Charge on the Revenue, which I do not ſay; and the difference I make herein is, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I found the Revenue of the Exciſe Let at a certain Rent of 530000 <hi>l. Per Annum,</hi> at my entrance to the Treaſury; which I firſt raiſed to 550000 <hi>l. Per Annum,</hi> and then to 560000 <hi>l. Per Ann.</hi> and it was never Let for more than that Sum under any certain Rent, and it was at the ſaid Rent of 550000 l. and no more, which Sir <hi>Robert</hi> made his Calcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations concerning the State of the Revenue to the King in 1675. about which ſomething will be ſaid in its proper place; but I mention this now, to ſhew that this Branch of the Revenue was no more impaired by me, <hi>than himſelf confeſſes the Cuſtoms to have been in my time:</hi> And it is as well known that I raiſed the Hearth-Money from 145000 <hi>l. Per Ann.</hi> to 162000 <hi>l. Per An.</hi> ſo that how he will make out <hi>the Revenues being im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paired from</hi> June 73. <hi>to</hi> March 75. <hi>and from</hi> March 75 <hi>to</hi> Lady Day 79. (as he ſays Fol. 21.) I do not underſtand. Since therefore the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Rent of the Exciſe was but 560000 <hi>l. Per An.</hi> and that by my way of Letting that Branch, betwixt a Farm at the ſaid certain Rent of 560000 l. and a management accountable to the King for the Overplus, there has ariſen a Surplus of 129000 l. and more beyond the ſaid Rent of 560000 l. I think it ought to be allowed as a Deduction, the Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue not being abated by it; but on the contrary is accounted at 560000 <hi>l. Per An.</hi> which is 10000 <hi>l. Per An.</hi> more than Sir <hi>Robert</hi> Accounts that Branch of the Revenue in his computations to the King, and is 30000 <hi>l. Per An.</hi> more than that part of the Revenue was Let for at my entrance to the Treaſury, which is the time taken for making the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon betwixt the Charge on the Revenue then, and at my leaving the Treaſury in 1679. ſo as in truth I might juſtly (though I do not) Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count all the encreaſes of the Revenue on any Branch of it in my time to ballance the increaſe of the Debt in the ſaid time, and then I am ſure the total of the Debt would be much leſs than it was when I entred to the Treaſury; but I have only Accounted this one Surplus, becauſe it could not be depended upon as any certain Rent, nor was it charged to any certain uſes, as all the certain Rent of the Exciſe was; but was appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cable to ſuch uſes as his Majeſty ſhould direct.</p>
            <p>My Fifth Deduction is 59588 <hi>l. to the Forces, &amp;c. which</hi> Sir <hi>Robert is pleaſed to allow.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>My Sixth Deduction is 35000 l. made uſe of to carry on the Service of the Navy, Ordnance, &amp;c.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:63646:6"/>
            <p>And my Seventh Deduction is 33000 l. for Tallyes ſtruck for Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions upon the two laſt Qarters of the Exciſe, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Theſe two laſt, <hi>viz.</hi> The ſixth and ſeventh I have put together, becauſe Sir <hi>Robert</hi> hath got <hi>Certificates in theſe two Particulars</hi> ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to contradict the reaſons given by me for the allowance of them as Deductions from the Charge; which I am glad to find is all he can pretend to contradict by any Authority; becauſe both the Sums together if they were not allowed, do amount but to 68000 l. and (as I have remarked before) he acknowledges, Fol. 13. <hi>that the Examiner hath miſtaken</hi> 58352 l. 9 s. 6 d. by a double Charge of ſo much of the Advance Money; ſo as the difference of my firſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation would be leſſened but 10000 l. if theſe two Sums were not to be deducted; but to ſhew that the matter of Fact is as I have ſaid in both theſe Particulars, I muſt ſhew that thoſe Certificates (if true) from the Ordnance, and Commiſſioners of Exciſe, are no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to the matter he pretends to make out by them: For as to the Ordnance I muſt needs ſay that it was not only the Office from which I could get very little of any Accounts in my whole time; but (notwithſtanding any Directions or Orders to the contrary) they would take no notice of that ſtop which was put to the Exchequer before my Time; but did apply thoſe Moneys to payments under that ſtop, which were ordered to the payments of Service forwards; ſo as it was impoſſible for me <hi>without intirely diſcharging the old</hi> Debt of that Office to have brought up their payments to the time of my leaving the Staff; and this makes the latter part of my time ſeem not to be provided for in that Office; but I do ſay that Tallyes ſtruck in my time to the Sum of 35000 l. (and which is reckoned as part of Sir <hi>Roberts</hi> Charge of 1419244 l. 16 s. 6 d.) were paid after my time, and the Money applyed by the preſent Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioners of the Treaſury in the ſtead of other Money which they muſt have paid: and Sir <hi>Robert</hi> himſelf knows that theſe Lords Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioners when they appointed a weekly Sum out of the Cuſtoms, of 2000 l. a Week, to diſcharge the Debt by Tallyes in Courſe, made uſe of the Tallyes ſtruck for the Navy, Ordnance and Forces in their Courſe too, and by that means had ſo much alſo of the 2000 l. a Week, which they applyed to the payment of the ſeveral Offices; as I doubt not but both the Commiſſioners of the Treaſury, and Paymaſter of the Forces will own: and to ſay this was no carrying the Offices of the Navy and Ordnance forward beyond the time of my leaving the Staff (becauſe it did not pay the whole Debt of thoſe two Offices) is no Argument; for untill the whole Debt can be paid, all pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are directed in courſe: and as I paid Debts before my time, (eſpecially to the Navy) ſo theſe Gentlemen muſt pay before their Time, and ſo muſt the Payments of any who ſhall ſucceed them, be applyed to the Payment of Ships and Yards, &amp;c. due before their time, unleſs it may be ſuppoſed that Ships abroad, &amp;c. (at the al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teration of the Treaſury into other hands) ſhall never be paid.</p>
            <p>But had Sir <hi>Robert</hi> ſent to the Office of the Ordnance for a Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificate to know, how much money I had paid them in all in my time, and what the accrued Debt was in the ſaid time, I doubt not but it would
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:63646:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>have appeared, that I had ſupplyed more Money to that Office, than would ſatisfie the whole Debt accrued in the ſaid time.</p>
            <p>As to the 33000 l. or there abouts (for I have not poſitively named that Sum) the matter of Fact is,</p>
            <p>That a ſtated Sum for Penſions was directed Yearly; ſo that if Tal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyes were not ſtruck, yet the Money remained in the hands of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners and Receivers of the Exciſe, until ſuch Tallyes were ſtruck: And that this Money did remain in their hands at my leaving the Staff (in part of a greater Sum) Sr <hi>Robert</hi> who was one appointed to ſtate their Accounts, cannot but know; As alſo that thoſe Commiſſioners, and Receivers (being to be laid aſide) did apply all the Caſh in their hands, to Tallyes in Courſe, and paid over this 33000 l. or there abouts, and the other Moneys in their Hands to diſcharge Tallyes in Courſe; And ſuch Tallyes as are reckoned part of the Charge, left by me on that Branch of the Revenue.</p>
            <p>But the ſaid Commiſſioners and Receivers of the Exciſe, might per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps give the preſent Lords Commiſſioners of the Treaſury an Account of little or no Caſh in their Hands, for the Reaſons aforeſaid; and yet this is no manner of Argument to prove what Sr. <hi>Robert</hi> would infer by his printed Paper: Unleſs, as he had leſſened thereby my Deductions, he had alſo leſſened the Charge, as he ought to have done; Knowing that with the Money in their Hands, at my leaving the Staff, they really paid as much in Tallyes, which are a part of the Charge ſaid to be left by me. And this if Sr. <hi>Robert</hi> would have Writ to them to Certifie, they muſt have owned to be True; And conſequently (from what I have ſaid con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning theſe two Deductions) I hope others will think <hi>them Reaſonable,</hi> although Sr. <hi>Robert</hi> do not.</p>
            <p>My eighth Deduction, is 15000 l. by Tallyes on the Cuſtomes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> This I muſt needs ſay was not ſo plainly expreſſed, as it ought to have been in my former Book: For theſe Tallyes were given to Mr. <hi>Kingdon</hi> (then Pay-maſter of the Army) and not being made uſe of by him before my leaving the Treaſury, they were ſince delivered up by him, to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Lords Commiſſioners of the Treaſury; ſo that they relate not to that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, which Sr. <hi>Robert</hi> hath taken the trouble to ſet down, Folio 18th. But I am ſure Sr. <hi>Robert</hi> knows it to be true, that ſuch Tallyes to the Sum of 15000 l. were delivered up by Mr. <hi>Kingdon</hi> to the Lords Commiſſioners, and he ought therefore in juſtice to have added them to that Sum of 4395 l. 3 s. 6 <hi>d. on</hi> Mr. Kents <hi>account,</hi> for the Knowledge of which I am behold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing wholly to Sr. <hi>Robert,</hi> becauſe otherwiſe I ſhould have been ignorant of that Deduction.</p>
            <p>My ninth and laſt Deduction, <hi>is,</hi> 2342 <hi>l. by Mr.</hi> Montagues <hi>Tallyes, which Sr.</hi> Robert <hi>is alſo pleaſed to Admit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Having gone through the Deductions, and having given the reaſons on which they are grounded, I hope they are ſo clear as will give every body ſatisfaction, and I ſhall now follow Sr. <hi>Roberts</hi> Method in his Folio 19. By taking</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:63646:7"/>
            <p>Firſt, the Examiners charge which was 1485570 l. 00 s. 00 d.</p>
            <p>Then Subſtract my former Deductions, which were 794930 l. 00 s. 00 d.</p>
            <p>Then Subſtract likewiſe the Deductions now to be added by Sr. <hi>Robert Howards</hi> aſſiſtance amounting to 58352 l. 9 s. 6 d. which is double Charged on that advance of Exciſe; And al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo 4395 l. 3 s. 6 d. Deducted on Mr. <hi>Kents</hi> Account of Tynn. <hi>Viz.</hi> 062747 l. 13 s. 00 d.</p>
            <p>Which together amounts to the Sum of 857677 l. 13 s. 00 d.</p>
            <p>And the remaining Charge will be 627892 l. 07 s. 00 d.</p>
            <p>I ſuppoſe Sr. <hi>Robert</hi> admits the Charge left on the three great Branches of the Revenue, by the Lord <hi>Clifford,</hi> to be as I have ſaid in my Book, <hi>viz,</hi> 469371 l. Becauſe he ſays nothing againſt it, and in that Compu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation are neither reckoned Advance-Monies, nor Monies unpaid to Ships, <hi>&amp;</hi>c. which amounted then to above Treble the Sum Sr. <hi>Robert</hi> now reckons to Sr. <hi>Iohn Narborow</hi>'s Fleet.</p>
            <p>And then the Charge left by me on the ſaid three Branches being but 627892 l. 07 s. 00 d.</p>
            <p>And the Charge by my Lord <hi>Clifford,</hi> being 469371 l. 00 s. 00 d.</p>
            <p>The Anticipations are increaſed in my time, <hi>viz.</hi> In Five years and three Quarters (although no Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies were given by Parliament, but what were appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priated and were ſo applied) only by the Sum of 158521 l. 07 s. 00 d.</p>
            <p>And as I have ſaid in my Anſwer to the Examiner, Folio 11th. I paid in that time, 318473 l. to the Gold-ſmiths, for their Perpetual In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt, which is almoſt double the Sum, increaſed upon the Anticipati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; Beſides the Rebellion of <hi>Virginia, &amp;c.</hi> which I have mentioned in that Anſwer, and therefore will not repeat them here.</p>
            <p>Before he cloſes his Account, Sr. <hi>Robert</hi> thinks fit to add to the Exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners Charge, <hi>A further Charge of</hi> 655634 l. 19 s. 6 d. By three particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Unpaid on the one Fifth of the Exciſe,</hi> 83000 <hi>l.</hi> 00 <hi>s.</hi> 00 <hi>d.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Debt of the Eaſtland Merchants.</hi> 186585 <hi>l.</hi> 19 <hi>s.</hi> 09 <hi>d.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Debt to the Navy upon the return of Sr.</hi> John Narborow's <hi>Fleet,</hi> 385648 <hi>l.</hi> 19 <hi>s.</hi> 09 <hi>d.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Of which he ſays the preſent Lords Commiſſioners of the Treaſury, have paid and ſatisfied.</hi> 478646 <hi>l.</hi> 18 <hi>s.</hi> 06 <hi>d.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſuppoſe the Examiner knew nothing of this matter, or certainly it would not have been Omitted by him; and I muſt here obſerve, that what Sr. <hi>Robert</hi> calls in me, <hi>a Charging the Revenue by Tallyes,</hi> he calls now in Others, <hi>A ſatisfying of Creditors,</hi> although it be the very ſame thing, and by Tallyes at a very great diſtance of Payment; Which
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:63646:8"/>if I had done, I perceive Sr. <hi>Robert</hi> would have made no uſe of for me, but to have added it to my Load of Anticipations.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>For the</hi> 83000 <hi>l,</hi> as I have already ſaid (and am very confident of the Truth of it) there was remaining in Mr. <hi>Kents</hi> hands at <hi>Lady-Day,</hi> 79. 52000 l. for 26. Weeks, of 2000 <hi>l. per</hi> Week on the Cuſtoms due to Sr. <hi>Iohn James</hi> and Partners; And for the remaining 31000 l. or for the whole 83000 l. I know no man that either did, or could have Protect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them from the Payment of it, according to the Act; If Mr <hi>Kent</hi> and Mr. <hi>Duncomb</hi> had proſecuted the Receivers of the Exciſe about it; Nor did I ever uſe any Authority or other means in that matter, betwixt them, than by perſwading them (as I did all men, who were concerned in the Kings Service) to accommodate one anothers Occaſions in their ſeveral Imployments, as far as their own ſafeties and conveniencies would permit: nor ſhould I have either Charged the King or any but the Receivers of the Exciſe themſelves, to have made ſatisfaction to any Body for any Sum which was due to them by virtue of the Act of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment out of the one Fifth of the Exciſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>For the</hi> 186585 l. 19 s. 9 d. (<hi>which Sr.</hi> Robert <hi>calls the Debt to the Eaſtland Merchants</hi> (and which I do not remember to be ſo much in my time as 40000 l.) it became a Debt by the Money of the Poll-Act falling ſo infinitely ſhort of what it was calculated to be by the Parliament; and for which there will be found very little of my directions, inſomuch that as I did not charge the Revenue with it in my time, ſo I take my ſelf to be no cauſe of the accruing of that Debt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>For the</hi> 385648 l. 19 s. 9 <hi>d. due to the Fleet upon the Return of</hi> Sir <hi>John Narborow:</hi> I wonder Sr. <hi>Robert</hi> will name it, when he is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring the State of the Debt left in 1679. with the Debt left in 1673. when he knows how vaſt a diſproportion there is betwixt that Debt to the Navy, and this in 1679. the Sum then due to the Fleet being much above a Million: So that I look upon this laſt Addition to be (as I have ſaid before) only to make a noiſe, beſides that Sir <hi>John Narborows</hi> Fleet came in ſince I was out of Imployment, and I thank God I am able to prove that there never was three Ships in all my time, that were not paid off with ready Money, and as ſoon as the Ship Books were perfected by which they were to be paid.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, if Sir <hi>Robert</hi> will give me leave to reckon <hi>as the Examiner hath done,</hi> Fol. 14. I may reckon the Advance of the Exciſe, <hi>viz.</hi> 211647 l. 10 s. 6 d. (for Sir <hi>Robert</hi> does acknowledge, <hi>Fol.</hi> 12. <hi>that I had only diſpoſed of</hi> 58352 l. 9 s. 6 <hi>d. of the</hi> 270000 <hi>l. advanced on that Branch</hi>) to be ſo much in ready Money, towards payment of the ſaid Fleet.</p>
            <p>So that upon the whole, I can no more conceive theſe three laſt particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars ought to be added to the Charge of the Revenue in my time, than the Examiner did, when he had Muſt'red up all he could think poſſible to be laid to that Account; and for the particular of the Ships, it is impoſſible but there muſt always be a Debt to be paid by whomſoever ſhall ſucceed in the Treaſury, only it will be leſs or bigger, as the Ships kept abroad are more or fewer in number, inſomuch that Sir <hi>Robert</hi> needs not give himſelf the trouble <hi>of proving this particular</hi> with that care which he ſeems to take about it.</p>
            <p>Moſt of Fol. 21. is taken up about Sr. <hi>Roberts</hi> Paper which was gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:63646:8"/>to the King the 5th of <hi>March</hi> 1675. by which <hi>he ſayes he intended other uſes than have been mentioned in my anſwer to the Examiner.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall ſay more to that Paper and ſome others of Sr. <hi>Roberts</hi> Schemes, as alſo to ſome managements of his own in his Office, and his miſtaken Certificates, (which I have in my Cuſtody) when my leiſure will give me leave to ask him the meaning of them: In the mean time his Paper of the 5th. of <hi>March</hi> being Printed in my Anſwer, every man is at li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty to make his own conſtruction of it; and not being preſent my ſelf at the delivery of it, I can only ſay what was told me when I received that Paper, from thoſe whom I do perfectly believe. One intent of the Paper Sr. <hi>Robert</hi> ſayes <hi>was to prevent thoſe frauds which had been commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the Exchequer;</hi> but ſince he hath not thought fit to inſtance any one particular of thoſe frauds, I am apt to believe, he either knows none, or none that he is willing to ſpeak of; for he knows, that if any fraud came to my knowledge (as ſome did) I made it always to be examined in publick; and I take it for one of the higheſt Vindications of my Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grity in the Treaſury, that Sr. <hi>Robert</hi> cannot charge me with any other applications of Money to my own uſe (out of thoſe great Sums which have paſſed through my hands) more than <hi>the Sum of</hi> 2747 l. 5 s. 11 d. beſtowed upon me at the making up of my Account as Treaſurer of the Navy: whereas there are good ſtore of inſtances of Lord Treaſurers heretofore, who from leſs Foundations of Eſtates than my ſelf, have left viſible Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numents of more Money laid out in ſome one ſingle Building of theirs, (beſides the Eſtates added in proportion to them) than I have got in near ſix years enjoyment of the ſame Office: So that ſince the blame can only be laid upon my management (who could be no wiſer than God had made me) and not upon any corrupt actings in my imployment; I do not only willingly undergo Sir <hi>Roberts</hi> Rebukes, but do acknowledg my own failings, and hope that by Sr. <hi>Roberts</hi> good Advice his Majeſty will for the future be ſerved as he ought to be.</p>
            <p>In the laſt Page of his Book Sir <hi>Robert</hi> ſays, <hi>it is only to give a ſhort Account, to ſhew his Judgment concerning Tallyes of Anticipation, and how extremely ſatisfied he is</hi> (which I verily believe) <hi>to ſee his Opinion appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by the preſent Lords Commiſſioners.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He has mentioned ſomething of the Anticipations alſo, Fol. 5. which I paſſed over in that place, becauſe they would more properly be ſpoke to both together, as alſo the matter of Intereſt depending upon ſuch Anticipa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, which is likewiſe in the ſaid Fol. 5.</p>
            <p>And in the firſt place I do agree with Sir <hi>Robert</hi> as much as any body elſe can do, that it is better to avoid Tallyes of Anticipation (where it can be done) than to make uſe of them; but that the Revenue muſt be ruined by them, Ideny; or that the Intereſt is left to any ſuch uncertainty as he would have believed; but that it muſt be by the knavery of the Lord Treaſurer, Chancellor of the Exchequer, or the ſworn Auditor of the Exchequer (before whom the Account is brought) if the King be wron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged in what Intereſt he pays upon ſuch Tallyes.</p>
            <p>I doubt not neither, but the preſent Lords Commiſſioners of the Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſury have endeavoured to avoid ſuch Tallyes, and ſo did I, till I found it impoſſible for me to help it, and (if I am not misinformed) although the preſent Lords Commiſſioners have ſpared 2000 l. a Week by their other
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:63646:9"/>retrenchments, to diſcharge Tallyes (which I was not able to ſpare, and ſupply the Kings other Occaſions) yet thoſe Tallyes which were in courſe, being paid, I hear and have good ground to believe true, that now the Lords Commiſſioners are neceſſitated to comply with ſome Lenders of Money ſo far, as to give them Tallyes of Anticipation to a conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Sum: nor do I know how it can be helpt, unleſs Sir <hi>Robert</hi> can be able to do more by his Legiſlative Capacity for remedy of the matter, than he will ever be able to do by his private; and if this be now the Caſe, as well as it was in my time, then by Sir <hi>Roberts</hi> Rule <hi>the Exche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer will ſtill be no wiſer than it hath been in knowing when Intereſt is to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mence upon ſuch Tallyes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>'Tis true that the Exchequer does not preſently know the Commence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Intereſt upon Anticipations; but I doubt not but the Lords Commiſſioners do take care, that the Vouchers (though called private ones) ſhall be as authentick as publick ones; and it is the Duty of a ſworn Auditor to ſee they be ſo, from whence they are entred in the Exche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer, and from that time the Exchequer does know the times of lending upon Tallyes of Anticipation, and conſequently the charge of Intereſt upon them; ſo that the Bug-Bear is made far more terrible than it is, although (as I have ſaid) it were better to be avoided, if the Kings ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſities will permit.</p>
            <p>I have now gone through Sir <hi>Roberts</hi> Book, and hope I have made ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear that the State of the Revenue at <hi>Lady-Day,</hi> 1679. was not as it hath been repreſented either by the Examiner or Sir <hi>Robert Howard;</hi> and ſince Sir <hi>Roberts</hi> friend (to whom he writes) had no curioſity to enquire into thoſe other parts of the Examiners Book which concerned the affairs of State therein mentioned, I ſhall repeat nothing upon that Subject, but conclude that his friend is ſatisfied in thoſe matters, which are of much the greateſt Concern to me; but I hope it will be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken notice of, that both the Examiner and Sir <hi>Robert</hi> (how much ſoever they may be ſtrangers to one another) have carried on the ſame deſign againſt me, as if it had been with the ſame hand; ſaving that Sir <hi>Robert</hi> has ſhewed himſelf to be the better Accomptant, by rectifying divers Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors in the Examiners Computations, and that he has been much more ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil than the Examiner in his Language.</p>
            <p>I ſhall conclude this Anſwer to Sir <hi>Robert Howard</hi> with this ſingle Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt to all my Country-men; That they would not believe any thing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt me by Reports, till they ſee it proved; And then as I ſhall deſire no other favour; ſo I doubt not but to be reſtored to the good Opinion of all ſuch, as have not particular prejudice againſt me.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>DANBY.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
